Guide to the Max Blechman Papers TAM.567
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Max Blechman Papers
1919-2005
1987-1995
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Blechman, Max
TAM.567
4.25 Linear Feet In 2 record cartons, 2 manuscript boxes, 1 flat box, 1 folder in shared housing, and 1 flat file folder
Max Belchman is an anarchist philosopher, author and editor. Drunken Boat was an anarchist journal edited by Blechman. Blechman also produced the anarcho-green journal SURGE. The collection contains correspondence, writings, ephemera and graphics relating to Drunken Boat, to Max Blechman's various activities, to the journal SURGE, and to Students Urging Resistance and Green Escalation.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The provenance of this collection is unknown, although materials appear to have been mailed to the Tamiment Library from Chicago on October 16, 2011. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2011.009 and 2023.015.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I, Drunken Boat and Max Blechman's Activities; and II, SURGE. Each is arranged alphabetically.
Biographical Note
Max Blechman (1971-), the editor of Drunken Boat, was born in New York City. He attended the Putney boarding school in Putney Vermont, received his BA at Eugene Lang College/New School for Social Research in 1994, and in that year moved to France and studied at the Sorbonne where he was awarded two degrees in philosophy. He is currently completing a Ph.D thesis on Rousseau at the Center for Research on Modern European Philosophy at Kingston University in the UK. His Drunken Boat publications are Drunken Boat: An Anarchist Journal of Literature and the Visual Arts (1991), Drunken Boat: Art, Rebellion, Anarchy (1994) and Revolutionary Romanticism: A Drunken Boat Anthology (1999). He has since published essays in political philosophy, aesthetics and utopia, mostly in the French press, twice guest-edited with Michael Lowy the French philosophical and literary journal, Europe, and recently translated and introduced Miguel Abensour's Democracy Against the State: Marx and the Machiavellian Moment (2011).
Drunken Boat appeared in the three book-length volumes listed above. In addition to Blechman, contributors included Paul Avrich, Hakim Bey, Diane Di Prima, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Judith Malina, Gary Snyder, and George Woodcock. SURGE was an anarcho-green periodical published by students of the Putney Boarding School in Putney, Vermont. There was one published issue and one unpublished issue. SURGE was also the acronym for two organizations, Students Urging Realism Growth and Evolution, which later became Students Urging Resistance and Green Escalation.
Scope and Contents
Series I, Drunken Boat and Max Blechman's Activities, contains correspondence, writings, graphics, ephemera and materials relating to this short-lived anarchist arts-related periodical, New York based but international in scope, and to the various activities of its editor, Max Blechman. Series II, SURGE, contains ephemera and other materials relating to this also short-lived anarcho-green periodical and to Students Urging Resistance and Green Escalation. This is a rich collection for the study of late twentieth century and Beat Generation anarchism, especially in relation to the arts. Series III consists of a flyer and a poster.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Manuscripts for publication.; Manuscripts; Correspondence.; Anarchism and art.; Anarchism -- United States -- Periodicals; Anarchism.; Castoriadis, Cornelius, 1922-1997; Woodcock, George, 1912-1995; Kent, Rockwell, 1882-1971.; Mac Low, Jackson; Löwy, Michael, 1938-; Gibson, Morgan, 1929-; Hakim Bey; Godard, Jean Luc, 1930-; Guerin, Daniel, 1904-; Knabb, Ken; Students Urging Resistance and Green Escalation; Blechman, Max; Blechman, Max; Drunken boat (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Di Prima, Diane; Avrich, Paul; Crass (Musical group); Snyder, Gary, 1930-; Malina, Judith, 1926-; Meselson, Amy; SURGE (Putney, Vt.); Rainer, Dachine; Bookchin, Murray, 1921-2006; Ferlinghetti, Lawrence
- Series I: Drunken Boat and Max Blechman's Activities
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I, Drunken Boat, contains Max Blechman's correspondence, mostly incoming and most related to Drunken Boat, principally to issues one and two, Blechman's writings published and unpublished, material in English and Frensh relating to his 1994 arrest in Paris for allegedly throwing stones during a demonstration, photocopies of writings by others by and about other anarchists, and anarchist printed ephemera and graphics. Additional Drunken Boat materials include submissions, letterhead, logos, artwork, and partial mock-ups of issues. There are also several files on the anarcho punk music group CRASS (Great Britain). Correspondence (most pertaining to Drunken Boat) or authors include: Paul Avrich, Hakim Bey, Murray Bookchin, Cornelius Castoriadis (Includes transcript of an interview), Diane Di Prima, Lawrence Ferlinghetti (from City Lights Bookstore, San Francisco), Morgan Gibson, Daniel Guerin, Jean-Luc Godard (interview),Rockwell Kent, Ken Knabb, Michael Lowy, Jackson MacLow, Amy Meselson, Dachine Rainier, Kenneth Rexroth, Gary Snyder and George Woodcock.
  - "Act Like Nothing's Wrong, Winston Smith-Last Gasp of San Francisco", 1990, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anarchism, Articles, Photocopies, 1979-1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anarchist Archives Project, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Anarchist Related Brief Printed Ephemera, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Anarchist Related Fliers, 1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Anarchist Related Serials, 1919, 1950-1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Avrich, Paul: Letters to Max Blechman, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Avrich, Paul: Papers at the Library of Congress: Max Blechman Employment, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Avrich, Paul: Writings, 1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Beck, Julia: Diary Entries (typed), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Benno, Benjamin: A Retrospective Exhibition, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bey, Hakim: "Storm Demon" (Who Was B. Traven?), undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Black, Bob: Letter to Max Blechman, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Black, Bob: Letters, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "The Black Freighter" [comic strip], Words: Bertolt Brecht, Illustration: Cliff Harper, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Blanchard, Daniel: Letter to Max Blechman (with photo of Drunken Boat), 1992, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Blechman, Max: Correspondence, Submissions, A-K, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Blechman, Max: Correspondence, Submissions, L-Z, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Blechman, Max, Drunken Boat Notebook, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Blechman, Max: Drunken Boat, 2nd Issue as Class Project (New School, New York City), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Blechman, Max: Letters from Miscellaneous Individuals, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Blechman,Max: Letters to Anonymous Individuals, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Blechman, Max: Letters to, A-B, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Blechman, Max: Letters to, C-D, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Blechman, Max: Letters to, E-G, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Blechman, Max: Letters to, H-I, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Blechman, Max: Letters to, J-L, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Blechman, Max: Letters to, M, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Blechman, Max: Letters to, N-R, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Blechman, Max: Letters to, S-Z, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Blechman, Max: Notes About Interview with Alan Ginsburg, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Blechman, Max: Paris Arrest, English Language Materials, Correspondence and Writings, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Blechman, Max: Paris Arrest, English Language Materials: Notebook and Clippings, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Blechman, Max: Paris Arrest, French Language Materials: Correspondence and Articles, 1994-1996 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Blechman, Max: Paris Arrest, French Language Materials: Periodicals, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Blechman, Max: Writings (Handwritten), undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Blechman, Max: Writings, Titled: "Anarchos: Arendt's Aesthetics of Action", undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Blechman, Max, Writings, Titled: "For the Total Man: Schiller and Marx's Philosophy of Self-Realization", undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Blechman, Max, Writings, Titled: "The Freedom to Be Before God Versus the Absolute Freedom of Being: Kierkegaard's Critique of Fichte", undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Blechman, Max, Writings, Titled: "From Anarchism to Fascism: Max Weber's Influence on the Political and Methodological Developement of Robert Michels", May 28 1992 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Blechman, Max, Writings, Titled: "Idealism versus Dogmatism", undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Blechman, Max, Writings, Titled: "In Defense of Abstract Expressionism", undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Blechman, Max, Writings, Titled: "Non-Servism: Portrait of the Anarchist as a Young Man", 1991 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Blechman, Max, Writings, Titled: "On the Very Idea of a Subversive Art History", 1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Blechman, Max, Writings, Titled: "Rebellion, Spontaneity, and the Poetry of the Moment", undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Blechman, Max, Writings, Titled: "The Spirit of Freedom: A Critique of Aquinas' Model for Salvation", undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Blechman, Max, Writings, "Titled: The Swollen Trunk of Time: A Gnostic Drama Featuring Artaud", undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Blechman, Max, Writings, Titled: "Toward an Aesthetic of Self-Determination: The Art of Camus and Bataille", undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Blechman, Max, Writings, Titled: "Toward an Anarchist Aesthetic", undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Blechman, Max, Writings, Untitled, 1993, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bookchin, Murray: Interview, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bookchin, Murray: H-bomb Writings and Bibliography, 1950s, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Cahill, Thomas: Letter to Max Blechman, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Cain, Seamas: (B)lackthorn [Anarchist] Theater [Duluth, MN], 1979, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Carburetor Records: Vinyl Records 6.5 Game Implications / Home Problems; Letters to Drunken Boat, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Castoriadis, Cornelius: Letter to Max Blechman, 1996, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Cohen, Ira: Letter to Max Blechman, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - CRASS (anarcho punk music group, Great Britain), folder 1 of 2, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - CRASS (anarcho punk music group, Great Britain), folder 2 of 2, 1980s (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - CRASS: International Anthem, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - CRASS: Photographs, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Deepsix Superstition, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Des Roches, Kay Unruh: "The Sea: Anarchy as Order", undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Di Prima, Diane: Correspondence with Max Blechman, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Drunken Boat Issue 3, Revolutionary Romanticism, A Drunken Boat Anthology, Correspondence [City Lights], 1999 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Drunken Boat Issue 3, Revolutionary Romanticism, "A Drunken Boat Anthology," Writings [City Lights], 1999 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Drunken Boat, Letterhead, Logo, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Drunken Boat: Mock Ups, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Drunken Boat Printed Ephemera, Undated (Box Shared Tamiment MSOS008, Folder 2)
  - Drunken Boat Oversize Graphics, Undated (Flat-file-folder 3)
  - Eliard, Thierry: Letters to Max Blechman and Writings, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Everett, Marty: Letter to Max Blechman, Jul. 10 1992 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Ferlinghetti, Lawrence: Letters to Max Blechman (in City Lights bookstore envelopes), also Picture of Ferlinghetti as a Priest, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Ferrua, Pietro: "Anarchists Seen by Painters", 1988 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Ferrua, Pietro: "Surrealisme et Anarchisme", 1982 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Flynt, Henry A.: "Against Participation: A Total Critique of Culture" (19pp), other materials, Oct 15 1993 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - French Language Stickers, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Funktionaries (Band), 1992 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Funke, Jacobson B.: Postcard to Max Blechman, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Gibson, Morgan: Letters to Max Blechman, 1992-1994, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Glavin, Paul (Black and Green): Letters to Max Blechman, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Graphs, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Grimm, Reinhold: "Poetic Anarchism? The Case of Hans Magnus Enzenberger", undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Grumble Butt, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Guerin, Daniel: Anarchism and Marxism (Writings), 1981 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Howe, Stewart: Letters to Max Blechman, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - "Intermediatism": Peter Lamborn Wilson aka Hakim Bey, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Industrial Worker: Excerpts on Anarchists, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Interview with Jean-Luc Godard, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Kanaan, Ramsey: Letters to Max Blechman, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Kent, Rockwell, 1933? (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Kiel, Mark W.: "Joseph Boshover: Anarchist Poet ", undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Knabb, Ken: Letter to Max Blechman, Mar. 24, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Koogan, Kevin: Correspondence with Max Blechman, Oct 1995 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Langlois, Walter G.: "Anarchism, Action, and Malraux", 1978 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Leake, Johnathan: Letter to Max Blechman, Jun 23 1994 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Left Bank Distribution: Letters to Max Blechman, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Letters with Drunken Boat Mastheads to Jackson MacLow et. al., 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Lowy, Michael: Letters to Max Blechman (French), 2001 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Machado, Wilfredo: Libro de Animales (Portfolio for Published Book, 1994), undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - MacLow, Jackson: Letters to Max Blechman, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Malina, Judith (Living Theatre): Letters to Max Blechman, 1993, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Mattisons, Michelle: Letter to Max Blechman, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Meselson, Amy: School Packets, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Mid-Atlantic Bl@cklist, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Mitzman, Arthur: Letters to Max Blechman, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Muhsam, Eric (1878-1934), undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Notes to the Reader, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Observations on Anarchy 54, undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Orr, Johnathan (Dispersal): Letter to Max Blechman/Drunken Boat, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Oversize Materials, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Petrovato John/Perennial Books: Letters to Max Blechman, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Photographs, US and France, with Cornelius Castoriadis, undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Publisher's Catalogs, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Rainier, Dachine: Letters to Max Blechman, 1992-1994 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Reiss, Robert, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Rexroth, Kenneth: Max Blechman Correspondence Regarding Rexroth, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sedgwick, Peter: "Out of Hiding: The Comradeships of Daniel Guerin", 1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Skaggs, Joey: Writings, 1960s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Snyder, Gary: Letter to Max Blechman, May 3, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Subscriber Index Cards, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "A Trilogy for 57 Uears Ago Monday" [1954 Barcelona Uprising], 1992 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Ultra Graphics, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Ward, Thomas, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Woodcock, George: Letters to Max Blechman, 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Minicassettes: Diane di Prima, Beruit #1, unmarked, 1995, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 004, Cassette 5-8)
- Series II: SURGE
  Series II, Surge, contains issue no. 1 (published), issue no.2 (unpublished), correspondence, a diary by Max Blechman, manifestos, artwork and printed ephemera, an interview with the False Prophets, and letters to Max Blechman from elected officials.
  - Form Letters from Senators Alphonese D'Amato and Daniel Patrick Moynihan and City Council President Andrew Stein, responding to Max Blechman's Letters, Oct 28, 1987-May 3, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - False Prophets Interview, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Max Blechman's Diary, Including notes, poetry, drawings, "happening" photos from the Putney School, Elm Lea Farm, Putney, VT, 1987-1988 (Box 3, Folder 13a)
  - SURGE Issue no. 1, Fall 1988 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - SURGE: Correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - SURGE: Issue no. 2 (Never Published): Camera Ready Complete Texts and Graphic Layout: all "Surge Collective" texts written by Max Blechman, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - SURGE (Students Urging Resistance and Green Escalation): Portfolio of Manifestos, Artwork, and Related Ephemera, 1989, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Series III. Posters, circa 2001; .25 Linear Feet in 1 folder in shared housing and 1 flat file folder
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of a poster printed by Max Blechman titled "Empire" and a printed flyer opposing Professor Karal Ann Marlings statements in the New York Times.
  - Open Letter to Karal Ann Marling, circa 2001 (Box Shared Tamiment 165, Folder 7)
  - "Empire" Poster, undated (Flat-file-folder 4 Left)